<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Several passages concerning the declared King of Scots, both by sea and land, communicated by letters, to persons of credit. Also, the confessions and speeches of the Laird Darsey, Major General Hurry, and Collonel Spotswood; made upon the scaffold at Edenburgh before their execution. With some remarkable passages concerning the City of London, several letters intercepted, and the advance of the two great Generalls, the Lord Fairfax and the Lord Cromwel into the north.</title>
            <author>S. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T57</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E603_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205816</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865078</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E603[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Several passages concerning the declared King of Scots, both by sea and land, communicated by letters, to persons of credit. Also, the confessions and speeches of the Laird Darsey, Major General Hurry, and Collonel Spotswood; made upon the scaffold at Edenburgh before their execution. With some remarkable passages concerning the City of London, several letters intercepted, and the advance of the two great Generalls, the Lord Fairfax and the Lord Cromwel into the north.</title>
                  <author>S. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.C. and are to be sold at the Royal Exchange, and without Cripplegate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on page 4: S.T.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Urry, John, --  Sir, d. 1650.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> SEVERAL PASSAGES CONCERNING THE Declared King of Scots, BOTH BY SEA and LAND, <hi>COMMUNICATED</hi> By Letters, to Perſons of Credit. ALSO, The Confeſsions and Speeches of the Laird
<hi>Darſey,</hi> Major General <hi>Hurry,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Spotſwood;</hi> made upon the Scaffold at <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> before their Execution. WITH Some remarkable Paſſages concerning the City of <hi>London,</hi> ſeveral <hi>Letters</hi> intercepted, and the advance of the two great Generalls, the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> and the Lord <hi>Cromwel</hi> into the NORTH.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>J. C.</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> and without <hi>Cripplegate,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:165653:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165653:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER FROM NEW CASTLE, CONCERNING The Confeſsions and Death of Col. SPOTSVVOOD, the Laird DARSEY, and Major General HURRY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom <hi>Scotland</hi> we have intelligence, that they have proceeded to execute Major Gen.
<hi>Hurry,</hi> the Laird <hi>Darſey,</hi> and Col. <hi>Spotſwood;</hi> theſe perſons (being within the pale of the Kirk) received more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour at their death then <hi>Montroſs,</hi> the manner I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to be thus. A Scaffold was built near the place where <hi>Montroſs</hi> was hanged, on which place was laid a block, and theſe three one after the other, were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165653:3"/> brought thither, and had their heads chopt off by the <hi>Hangman.</hi> They had
<hi>Miniſters</hi> with them to their end, and were exceeding penitent, eſpecially Col.
<hi>Spotſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> who being deſired that he would not conceal at his death, any thing that troubled his mind, or lay hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy upon his Conſcience, (amongſt other things which he confeſſed to be a great grief unto him,) he ſaid to this effect following.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſubſtance of the Confeſſions of Col.</hi> Spotſworth, <hi>the Laird</hi> Darſey, <hi>and Major Gen.</hi> Hurry.</head>
               <p>THat he was guilty of a moſt horrid murther, and that he thought many times that he ſaw the bloody wounds of Dr. <hi>Doriſlawes,</hi> in whoſe death himſelf was an inſtrument being preſent with the reſt, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging Gods juſt judgement upon him, for this and other many great ſins which he had committed with deſerved death, he prayed that others might take warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by what did befall unto him, That he loved and honoured his King, and what he did was to promote his ſervice, wiſhing that he might be well dealt with, if he came amongſt them; ſaying, that it was an ill beginning at this conjuncture of time, to fall ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely upon ſuch as had ſo near relation to him, yet did he ſubmit to the juſtice of the ſentence, in relation to himſelf. The Laird <hi>Darſey</hi> ſhewed much penitency and humility upon the Scaffold, and after a ſalutation to thoſe of his acquaintance that were about him, he made a ſhort ſpeech, acknowledging his misfortune to be brought this way to his end; and after a ſhort prayer in private, prepared himſelf for the block: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165653:3"/> Gen. <hi>Hurry</hi> laid ſome blame upon others, as being drawn into that ſnare, and in his deportment beheaved himſelf ſomewhat like a Souldier then the reſt. A great number of people were preſent, the objects af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording matter of joy to ſome, and grief to many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: After execution was done, their bodies were carried away, and buried in Chriſtian burial. There is brought priſoner to <hi>Edenburgh</hi> a French Marqueſs, who was taken in the North of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> He confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that he came thither with a reſolution to joyn with
<hi>Montroſs,</hi> himſelf and ſome others having Commiſſion from their declared King, and Letters of importance which are likewiſe taken: He ſaith, that he heard not that
<hi>Montroſs</hi> was taken and executed before he came thither, in which he may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be believed; for had he known that, he would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have been ſo wiſe as to kept away, he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſafe cuſtody, and the report goes, that he wil be tryed for his life, as an invader of that Kingdom. Another which would ſurely have gone to pot, had he been taken, was a Brother to <hi>Montroſs,</hi> who ſtriking in with a ſmall Frigot, thinking alſo to come to his Brother, having knowledge as ſoon as he came to ſhore, what had befallen to his Brother, made an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape by another veſſel; but the Frigot wherein he came is taken, and in it ſeveral Commiſſions from their declared King, and a Letter from him to <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſse,</hi> the contents whereof was, that he ſhould proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his Commiſſion with effect, untill ſuch time as he received farther Orders or directions from him; aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<hi>Montroſs</hi> and others with him, that his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were ardent towards them, with many ſuch like expreſſions and promiſes, which when he came thither
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165653:4"/> in perſon ſhould be really obſerved; but (ſaith the eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated <hi>Presbyterian)</hi> this was at a time when our decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Kings Majeſty</hi> had no other ſtring to his bow: yet now we hope to find better things from him, if he comes hither, and hath about him ſuch perſons as our unerring Church and State ſhall appoint: And thoſe of this perſwaſion are the onely men that long for his coming, and are ſo confident, that his purpoſes are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al therein, that I have ſeen a Letter which one wrote to his Friend, meerly upon a report or noyſe, which ran as far as <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> about two dayes ſince, that their King was landed at
<hi>Sterling,</hi> unto which the ſubſcriber gave ſo much credit, that to uſe his own words, he ſaith; that he hoped to attend his Majeſty the next morning. At preſent all is quiet, not any Letters from his declared Majeſty to the Parliament, ſince <hi>William Murry</hi> came, who is returned back again about 10. dayes ſince, with a letter from them in a very ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive manner, directed <hi>To his moſt excellent Majeſty,</hi> The matter incloſed is a covering for their proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Montroſs,</hi> the Laird
<hi>Darſey,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Hurry,</hi> and Col. <hi>Spotſwood,</hi> perſwading his Majeſty that there is a vaſt difference in the caſe betwixt him and them, for they valued their King to be worth 10000 ſuch, and that his Majeſty may not doubt hereof, they affirm that they have an Army of 12000 men already in pay, which they promiſe to be his Guard, in caſe he puts himſelf on that account, and that they have liſted 13000 more, to be ready at beat of Drum, to ſerve him againſt Sectaries, &amp;c. which is all at preſent from</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Newcaſtle
<date>7. Jan. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your aſsured Friend S. T.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165653:4"/>
               <head>A Letter from a Gentleman in <hi>London,</hi> to his Friend in the <hi>Countrey.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>ACcording to your Requeſt, I ſhall abreviate from you here, what you have not leaſure to read at large. The firſt thing conſiderable in order to time, is, an Act of</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>for ſetling the Militia of the City of</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>Subburbs of</hi> London, <hi>and parts adjacent within the weekly Bill of mortality, nominating a Committee which have power to raiſe, leavy, and array men; and to appoint Collonels, Captains,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>with power to lead and conduct the ſaid forces, as occaſion ſhall require, into any part of the Common-wealth of</hi> England, <hi>to appeaſe all inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Act for Creditors and Priſoners, ordered to be debated again the next week.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Act for the probate of wills read and committed. The Act for bringing in of a new Repreſentative, committed and ordered to be brought in again on</hi> Wedneſday <hi>next. The Lord</hi> Gerard Scalph, <hi>Commiſſioner from the States of</hi> Holland, <hi>hath had Audience, the buſineſs to be ſomewhat further conſidered. The Lord</hi> Cromwel <hi>hath made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to the houſe, touching the ſtate and condition of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>the forces left there, under what mediate Command, as alſo the ſtrength of the Enemy, the Towns remaining in their poſseſſion, and ſeveral other things in relation to that Countrey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This week was a Common-conncel ſummoned by vertue of a Warrant, ſigned by divers Commoners of the City of</hi> London, <hi>without the Lord Mayor (a thing not uſual) which they grounded upon an Act of Parliament, dated the 28. of</hi> Febr. 1648. <hi>which Act inableth any ten of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165653:5"/> the Common-counce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lmen to call a Common-councel, in caſe the Lord Mayor ſhould refuſe; but the Lord Mayor is ſo far from refuſing, that he acts with them for the good and welfare of the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and both himſelf and the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were at this time preſent, we have intelligence that</hi> Hurry <hi>and ſome other eminent perſons which were taken with the Marqueſs of</hi> Montroſs <hi>are beheaded at</hi> Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, <hi>by which we may ſee the condition of earthly things, and that miſchance ſtandeth next to good fortune, and how ſuddainly they that make not conſcience of their wayes, may fall and leave nothing behind them, but ignominy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach. Much debate hath been this week about the publick Affaires of the Nation, and it is agreed that the two great lights in our horizen, the L. G.</hi> Fairfax, <hi>and the L.</hi> Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, <hi>ſhall advance</hi> Northwards; <hi>who both excelling in wiſdom and Martial-knowledge, are deſervedly above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be eſteemed and honoured: much talk hath been within a day or two, that the declared King of</hi> Scotland <hi>is taken, ſomeſay by the</hi> Scots <hi>with a</hi> Breda <hi>net, others ſay by the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Fleet, as he was going thither, what is of certain time muſt produce, onely at preſent take what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from moſt aſſured hands,</hi> viz. <hi>That he is gone out of</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>for they were deſirous to be eaſed of him; and beſides, ſome Ships that attended for him,</hi> Vantrump <hi>had about 20. ſayle, which according to vulger report, were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct him: About
10. of theſe were ſeen to ſayle towards</hi> Jerſey, <hi>and if there were more, its thought they ſayled for</hi> Scotland, <hi>and then its likely he is taken, or elſe they that were to be his Convoy, returned back again upon ſight of the</hi> Parliaments <hi>Ships, which ride on the</hi> Northern <hi>Coaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>London
<date>15. June, 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
